we are going to take a look at the
future of css the google io 2022 just
finished and it was packed with sessions
and keynotes about browsers and the
future of the web
really cool super new or coming soon css
features were announced i made a list of
the ones that i like the most and that
is exactly what i want to share with you
today
color mix allows you to mix colors on
the browser and it looks like this here
we are getting a color that is 50 red
and 50
blue but if we want to we can also
choose the ratios of the mix by
specifying a percent so here we would be
mixing 30 red and 70
blue like it was said on the keynote
color mix is especially useful to derive
other colors from a brown color maybe
mixing it with white or with black to
make it lighter or darker by saving the
brown color in a css variable and using
it later inside of color mix
accent color allows you to change the
color of those html elements that have
been historically very hard to customize
like radio buttons or check boxes
progress bars and range sliders
if we want to change the colors of those
elements we have to do it by ourselves
manually by changing the background
color and the border color the hover
stays the focus states among many other
things that is hard to remember with
accent color all we have to do is tell
to the browser what is the accent color
of those elements in the browser we
change the background color the border
color and all those things for us if we
have these elements for example and i
want to make them pink or red or blue
all i have to do is change the accent
color property and with one line all
their styles will be changed
for text to be easy to read there has to
be a good contrast between the
background color and the text color
black on top of blue or white on top of
yellow does not look good instead of us
having to pick what color has the best
contrast with our background color we
can instead use color contrast to let
the browser do it for us here we have a
box with a background color of red
now we want to do is we want to set the
color of the text of that box to
whatever color the browser thinks has a
better contrast with red so we call
color contrast and we give it the red
color then the browser will see if white
has a good contrast with red or if black
has a good contrast with red the best
color with the best contrast is going to
be what the text color of our box will
be color contrast by default is going to
return either white or black no more but
this is already good because the browser
knows what looks good so for example the
browser is not going to give you black
text on top of a blue background or
yellow text on top of a yellow
background but that is not the best
part instead of only getting white or
black from color contrast we can also
provide options for the browser to
choose from the way you use it is like
this first we write the background color
in this case it will be blue then we do
vs or versus and then we write the color
options that the browser can choose from
so here the browser will check and
choose among the colors pink yellow and
green to see who has the best contrast
against a background of color blue and
then the browser is going to give us the
winner color
inert is not really a css properties
more like an html attribute inert allows
you to basically freeze sections of your
page any html element with the inert
attribute will not receive any clicks
focus events interactions nothing from
the user this is very useful if for
example you want to freeze a button
after the user clicked it once or if you
are sending a form and you don't want
the user to click anywhere else you can
freeze the whole form by adding the
inert attribute to the form html element
now before we continue with the rest of
the list please remember that if you
want to learn to code for free with me
in hangout and please click the link
below because there we have free courses
on javascript python go react react
native redux
many many other things all of them for
free click the link below and i will see
you there
has allowed you to style a parent
depending if it contains a specific
child this wasn't possible before before
we could only a style a child if it was
inside of a parent here we could apply
styles to a button if it was inside of a
form but we couldn't add a styles to the
form if it contained a button has
completely fixes this to add styles to a
form if it contains a button all we have
to do is this
and that is super super useful you can
now for example add styles to a list
item if the list item contains a link or
you can change the way a link looks like
if the link is around an image or you
can go a little crazy and you can change
the style of a form if the form has a
button and the button has the mouse on
top of it
there are two viewport units that are
very well known vw and vh vw gives you
the viewport width and vh gives you the
viewport height viewport is the area or
the window from which the website is
being seen in a mobile screen since we
can't resize windows in mobile 100 vh
will give you the total
height of the screen and 100 vw will
give you the total width of the screen
but now we have even more units for
mobile sizes we have lvh which is
largest viewport height we have svh
which is the smallest viewport height
and we have the vh which is dynamic
viewport height largest will be the size
of the screen without the navigation bar
smallest will be the size of the screen
with the navigation bar and dynamic will
be a size that changes depending if the
navigation bar is shown or not
this code might look very familiar to
you when we do css we have to repeat
ourselves sometimes we want to make sure
that we only apply some styles to the
children of certain parents in our
example we repeat the nav selector three
times when we want to target the list
inside of the nav and the list item
inside of the list inside of the nut the
nest rule allows you to turn our code
from what we just seen to something like
this as you can see it looks much much
better is way easier to read and we
don't have to repeat enough even once we
write it one time and then we write the
children inside of it nested and what we
used so far is the nested selector sign
which is this ampersand sign but we can
also use the add nest rule the add nest
rule gives us more power when nesting
selectors that do not start with an
ampersand with the nest rule we could do
something like this
and that is the same as doing this
as you can see the ampersand sign
becomes a placeholder which is very cool
because you can do very exciting stuff
the scope rule allows you to scope your
styles or basically isolate them into
their own style bubble take this code
for example as you can see here we are
changing the styles of the navigation
and the title class depending on them
being inside of a header or inside of an
aside tag or for example if we want to
create a dark theme and then maybe a
lighter theme and maybe a purple theme
we could do something like this as you
can see a scope makes it so much easier
to write isolate and think about our
styles so please compare what we just
did using scope and dark light and
purple theme with what we would have to
do if we didn't use a scope at all now
you tell me what looks better and you
tell me what is easier to read and
understand
before the container rule css elements
could only respond to changes in the
width of the window this is how we do
responsive design if the screen becomes
smaller then we modify and move things
inside of the page but that was only by
listening to the changes in the width of
the window with the container rule
elements can listen for changes not on
the window but on their parents here we
are creating a container we name it
header container and we say that we want
to know about the changes to its size
then we say that when the header
container has a minimum width of 600
pixels the display property of the
navigation must be flex
with the custom media rule we can create
media query variables and just reuse
them here we are creating dark mode
variable light mode variable landscape
portrait iphone variable whatever we
want and then all we have to do is reuse
them when we're writing our media
queries without this new feature our
code would look something like this
there will be a lot of copy pasting and
maybe many mistakes now you tell me what
looks best now please let me know in the
comments which one is your favorite css
property mines are all the color ones i
like accent colors i like contrast color
i like color mixing i think they're
pretty pretty cool and i really like the
media query variables they're very very
sexy let me know what you think what was
your favorite as always stay happy stay
free it kimchi come hamidah salmon heyo
see you on the next one bye